בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's דף daf is ס"ו, Samech-Vav, sixty-six. Twenty-second
day of the עומר, Omer, is that right? No, twenty-first day of
the עומר. Omer. All right, just to check who's counting. All right,
anyway, we pick up on ס"ה עמוד ב' Samech-Hei Amud Bet and
we are dealing with a central question. We're a little behind, so
we've got to focus today. We're dealing with a central, central question
about קידושין, kiddushin, the need for witnesses not only to prove that
it occurred, but without the witnesses, the קידושין kiddushin did not take
place. Do you need the witnesses? They're constitutive of the קידושין. kiddushin.
Okay, and we're trying to prove it one way or the other.
That was the question raised. Would it work if there was only
one witness and both parties agreed? So you technically don't have two
witnesses, but presumably you know that it happened. And that's the question.
And we're trying to prove it from the different claims about he
says we got married and she says we didn't. Well, where were
the witnesses? So we have to insert into those claims that he's
claiming they were married with witnesses and the witnesses aren't present. Or
the debate between בית הלל Beis Hillel and בית שמאי Beis Shammai
about a husband and wife that, ex-wife, ex-husband and ex-wife that are
in an inn. Do we say being in the inn assumes that
they've had sex and that they're married? Where are the witnesses? So
that was an easy one. There are witnesses that see that they
went into the inn together. And the question is: does witnesses of
going into seclusion constitute witnesses of the actual act of sex? Okay,
but again, that is the assertion and that we need witnesses. Without
witnesses the קידושין kiddushin did not take place. So we pick up
on ס"ה עמוד ב' Samech-Hei Amud Bet with the following, about
five lines from the top, last two words of the line: אמר
רב יצחק בר שמואל בר מרתא משמיה דרב, Amar Rav Yitzchak bar
Shmuel bar Marta mishmei deRav, so in the name of רב, Rav,
המקדש בעד אחד אין חוששין לקידושיו. Hamikadesh be'ed echad ein chosheshin lekidushav.
If somebody does קידושין kiddushin with only one witness, there is no
concern, no קידושין kiddushin took place, nothing happened here. ואפילו שניהם מודים,
Va'afilu shenehem modim, even if both parties, husband and wife, agree, doesn't
matter. Without two witnesses, nothing happened. אמר רבה בר רב הונא: Amar
Rabbah bar Rav Huna: המקדש בעד אחד, בי דינא רבא אמרי אין
חוששין לקידושיו. Hamikadesh be'ed echad Bei Dina Rabba amri ein chosheshin lekidushav.
So now רבה בר רב הונא Rabbah bar Rav Huna said if
somebody marries a woman with only one witness present, the big בית
דין, beis din, אמרי amri say, אין חוששין לקידושיו, ein chosheshin lekidushav.
no concern, no קידושין kiddushin happened. So that's clearly becoming the anonymous,
the dominant voice in the גמרא. Gemara. מאן בי דינא רבא? Man
Bei Dina Rabba? Who is the big בית דין? beis din? רב.
Rav. So the authority, one sort of one generation earlier,
רב. Rav. ואיכא דאמרי: Ve'ika de'amri: אמר רבה בר רב הונא אמר
רב, Amar Rabbah bar Rav Huna Amar Rav, that no, this original
statement was in the name of רב. Rav. המקדש בעד אחד Hamikadesh
be'ed echad, בי דינא רבא Bei Dina Rabba אמרי amri אין חוששין
לקידושיו. ein chosheshin lekidushav, So רב Rav says that the big בית
דין beis din says it's no concern. מאן בי דינא רבא? Man
Bei Dina Rabba? Who is the big בית דין? beis din? רבי.
Rebbe. Okay, so either רב Rav or רבי, Rebbe, obviously now we're
having a very dominant voice that it is not a problem at
all. You wouldn't even say it's a problem מדרבנן miderabbanan either. Correct,
correct, that's a good point, because then once you add a דרבנן,
derabbanan, it's not like being דרבנן derabbanan and not doing something on
שבת. Shabbos. It has all these huge consequences, the woman needs a
גט get and all that thing, so it's like either or.
Okay, מתיב רב אחדבוי בר אמי: Masiv Rav Achadvoi bar Ami: שנים
שבאו ממדינת הים. Shnayim shebau mimedinas hayam. Okay, here's another case to
challenge it. Two people come from מדינת הים medinas hayam ואשה עמהם,
ve'ishah imahem, with a woman. Now it's already just sad that it
doesn't say three people come from מדינת הים. medinas hayam. Two people
come with a woman, וחבילה עמהם, Vechavilah imahem, and with a bundle.
Okay, we're like with luggage. A woman and the bundle. A woman
and luggage. זה אומר, Zeh omer, guy number one says: זו אשתי
וזה עבדי וזו חבילתי, Zu ishti vezo avdi vezo chavilah sheli, this
is my wife, this is my slave, this is my luggage. וזה
אומר: Vezeh omer: No, זו אשתי וזה עבדי וזו חבילתי. Zu ishti
vezo avdi vezo chavilah sheli. No, this is my wife, that's my
slave, you're my slave, and that's my bundle. ואשה אומרת: Ve'ish omeres:
אלו שני עבדי וחבילה שלי, Elu shenei avadai vechavilah sheli, both of
you are my
slaves and it's my bundle. So what a great scenario. Okay, so
ההלכה היא: halachah es: צריכה שני גיטין, Tzrichah shenei gittin, she needs
a גט get from each one of them וגובה כתובתה Vegoves kesuvatah
and she can collect her כתובה kesuvah מן החבילה min hachavilah from
the bundle, from the luggage, like whatever value has the luggage. Because
according to her the luggage is hers, according to each of them
if they give her a גט get she was their wife, so
they have to pay her כתובה, kesuvah, so ממה נפשך mimah nafshach
she's entitled to at least a כתובה kesuvah out of the luggage.
Okay, the value of the כתובה kesuvah out of the luggage. Now
היכי דמי? heichi dami? Now what's the case? Because the question is:
why does she need a גט get just because one of them
claims that she's his wife? Right? We learned before: he says she's
his wife, she says no you're not, right? She doesn't need a
גט, get, right? He's just bound by it. So that's going to
be like one question, why does she even need a גט? get?
But what we're also going to ask is: where are the witnesses
in any of this? Okay, היכי דמי, heichi dami, what's the case?
Because how can a woman be a witness here? She's not, nobody's
a witness. No, I don't mean to the marriage, I mean that
they're accepting her as her claim, possibly. It's not a witness,
it's just like if you have litigants in a court. I say
that car is mine, you say it's yours, we have to go
to court to fight it out. But a woman should be respected
as a litigant. Yes, she can't be a witness, but she can
be a litigant. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says היכי דמי, heichi
dami, what's the case? אי דאית לה סהדי להאי ואית לה סהדי
להאי. I dei is lah sahadei lehai ve'is lah sahadei lehai. So
if each guy's got witnesses that this woman is their wife, okay.
Out but it will be it should be respected. As a litigant,
yes. She can't be a witness but she can be a litigant.
Okay. So, okay. So the גמרא Gemara says, היכי דמי, heichi dami,
what's the case? אי דאית ליה סהדי להאי ואית ליה סהדי להאי,
ei de-is lei sahadei le-hai ve-is lei sahadei le-hai, so if each
guy's got a witness- got witnesses that that this woman is their
wife, okay, because again, how could there be a marriage without witnesses?
So מי מצייא אמרה אלו שני עבדיי וחבילי שלי, mi matzi amra
elu shenei avadai ve-havilei sheli, how can she have any claim that
she's not their wives? Now you could have said if there's two
and two they neutralize each other, but maybe the גמרא Gemara would
be saying, well, you know, but at least that would establish you
know the presumption that she's one of their wives. Anyway, how her
claim be believed in the presence of witnesses claiming there was קידושין?
Kiddushin? Okay. אלא לאו בעד אחד, ela lav be-ed echad,
it must be one witness. Now again, that doesn't really explain it,
right? Because what the witnesses are sort of neutralizing one another. So
anyway, let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. But the reason of
וסבירא ve-savira does any of this make sense? עד אחד כשיניים בהימנותא,
ed echad ke-shnayim be-heimanuta, which is exactly what the גמרא Gemara says.
Even if it's one witness, if the witnesses are going up against
each other, they neutralize one another, and we're back to square one.
So none of this makes any sense. Like why would she require
a גט? get? It's only their claim, and their claim that this
is my wife doesn't make- mean that she needs a גט. get.
Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says, אלא למשרי לעלמא דכולי עלמא לא
פליגי דשריא, ela le-mishrei le-alma de-kulei alma lo peligi de-sharya, you're right.
There's no objective basis to require for a גט get because if
there would be it would be one witness against one or two
against two or whatever. Anyway, so clearly there's no objective basis. והכי
הכי קאמר, ve-hacha hachi ka'amar, צריכה שני גיטין כדי לגבות כתובתה מן
החבילה. tzericha shenei gittin kedei ligbot ketubatah min ha-havila. Okay. So כדי
לגבות כתובתה מן החבילה. kedei ligbot ketubatah min ha-havila.
So she does not objectively require a גט. get. It's just a
he-said-she-said type of thing. And we'd have to say like we said
before, that they're claiming yeah, I married her five years ago and
there were witnesses. Who remember- who knows where those witnesses are? Right?
Does anybody rem- people- everybody here remember who their עדי קידושין edei
Kiddushin was? So, you know, okay. You're this guy you do. Good
for you. All
right
anyway, so they're saying there were witnesses at the time, there're no
witnesses now. It's all a he-said-she-said type of thing. So fine that's
all fine but then who why does she need a גט? get?
No, what it's saying is that she doesn't need a גט, get,
but that nobody would be entitled to this- to the luggage.
It all comes down to the luggage! Exactly. Nobody would be entitled
to the luggage because it's all- everybody claims it's their luggage, and
the only way somebody would be entitled to the luggage would be
if they decided to give her a גט. get. Why they would
decide to give her a גט get who knows since הלכתית halachikly
she doesn't require it, and you know, why do they need to
give her a גט? get? But somehow if they decided to give
her a גט, get, then she would be entitled to collect her
כתובה ketubah from the luggage. All right, so then what's the חידוש?
chiddush? If it's not demanding anything, there's no חידוש chiddush about this.
So it says, רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, the חידוש chiddush is that
it's going according to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, דאמר מטלטלי משתעבדי לכתובה,
de-amar metalteli mishta'abdei le-ketubah, that the חידוש chiddush is that you can
collect your כתובה ketubah from luggage, that it doesn't have to be
land, it can even be chattel. All right, so anyway again that
was a case where the- even if you demanded witnesses, they're not
present. If they were present, then that sounds like the case, the
case does not sound like there are witnesses present that would have
complicated the whole scenario. Okay. Now yes. So in many other of
the cases, let's say יבום, yibum, דהשתא de-hashta let her have חליצה,
chalitzah, like what do you lose? But over here, like we seem
more reluctant to require גיטין. gittin. Yes, because well no, I mean
the cases we require חליצה chalitzah are not are cases where
yeah, I mean like I said before I don't want to start
starting doing a whole comparison, you know, but the basic point is
that if he basically doesn't require a גט, get, to say that
she require- if- it's like if you know you could secure a
גט, get, then maybe it would be not a big deal, but
it would still be a big deal. He'd be אסור בקרובותיה, assur
bi-krovoteha, she'd be אסורה לכהן, assura le-kohen, there'd be a lot of
big consequences, okay, but the other point is that you don't want
to say a woman needs a גט get because then what- because
then it creates enormous as we know in the contemporary עגונה agunah
reality. Okay, so you're absolutely correct. We are very, very reluctant if
there's no need for a גט get to not say, oh well
just give her a גט get anyway. All right, so now the
גמרא Gemara says like this, although it's not like we didn't have
that, but we're extremely reluctant because it's- it's extremely onerous on the
woman. All right, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, now
what's- what's- what's the upshot about this? מאי הוי עלה? mai havya
alah? What was- you know, what was the upshot of all this
discussion? So far we're like there's a lot of אמוראים Amoraim insisting
that you need two עדים, edim, but it's very very hard even
if there's not evidence against it in the Tannaitic material, because you
know, it's very hard to find any evidence for it in the
Tannaitic material. So like what's the conclusion? So רב כהנא אמר אין
חוששין לקידושין, Rav Kahana amar ein chosheshin le-kiddushin,
no problem, you don't even have to worry that there's a קידושין.
Kiddushin. רב פפא אמר חוששין לקידושין, Rav Pappa amar chosheshin le-kiddushin, רב
פפא Rav Pappa says no, no, no, I'm still a little bit
concerned, you know, does that mean דאורייתא? de-oraita? Maybe it's good. Maybe
דרבנן de-rabbanan like Michael said דרבנן, de-rabbanan, I'm not willing to say
it's not a problem at all. אמר ליה רב אשי לרב כהנא,
amar lei Rav Ashi le-Rav Kahana, so רב אשי Rav Ashi says
to רב כהנא Rav Kahana who said that it's not a problem
at all, מה דעתך, mah da'atach, where- where's- what's your opinion? Where'd
you get your opinion- your- your position from that it's not a
קידושין Kiddushin at all? So you must have gotten it from מה
דעתך דילפת דבר דבר מממון, mah da'atach de-yalpat davar davar mi-mammon, you
learned out a גזירה שוה gezeira shava because it says על פי
שנים עדים יקום דבר al pi shenei edim yakum davar and it
says כי מצא בה ערות דבר. ki matza bah ervat davar. So
there's a word דבר davar by דבר שבערה davar she-be-erva with the
phrase דבר שבערה, davar she-be-erva, things relating to personal status,
marriage and- Okay, דבר דבר מממון. davar davar mimmamon. Let's look at
דבר דבר מממון. davar davar mimmamon. One minute. אם עלה im ala
where it says על פי שנים עדים יקום דבר, al pi shenayim
eidim yakum davar, הודאת בעל דין כמאה עדים דמי. hoda'at ba'al din
keme'ah eidim dami. So there we say that if I admit that
I owe Michael a thousand dollars, then that's like there's witnesses and
I owe him a thousand dollars. So even when you need witnesses
in court, the witnesses for monetary matters are not without witnesses—like if
I borrow a thousand dollars from Michael and there are no witnesses,
it's not like the debt doesn't exist, right? The purpose of witnesses
is only to prove it, and therefore if I admit it, it's
considered to be that it actually, that's accepted, and therefore I owe
him the money. So if that's true by money and we only
learn out the need of witnesses for קידושין kiddushin from the witnesses
by monetary matters, let's say the same thing here. אף מודה במקצת
אין
בקידושין af modeh bemiktzat ein bekiddushin though. Okay fine, but at least
for the function of witnesses, הודאת בעל דין כמאה עדים דמי. hoda'at
ba'al din keme'ah eidim dami. If the parties agree, let that be
considered like good testimony, meaning where do we get the idea—and here's
a key phrase which I haven't used so far, but the phrase
used in, you know, in the to sort of to describe the
difference is whether they're considered עדי בירור edei beirur or עדי קיום.
edei kiyum. Are the witnesses just to clarify what took place, to
prove what took place, or is the purpose of witnesses, right, you
know, to establish something, to actually create the reality? Without the witnesses,
the thing didn't happen. Okay, so what he's saying is by monetary
matters, you owe the money whether or not there were witnesses. All
the function of the witnesses are is to prove it in court.
And if you have other ways of proving it or if the
guy admits it, then he still has to pay. So if you're
learning, here it says על פי שנים עדים יקום דבר al pi
shenayim eidim yakum davar and here it says ערבת דבר, ervat davar,
how do you all of a sudden say that in the case
of of קידושין kiddushin and personal status issues, let me remember by
גיטין gittin as well, right although that might have been that the,
that the physical גט get is not considered a גט get without
witnesses. Okay, but there as well, the whole idea was it doesn't
take place without witnesses. Well how do you learn that out if
the basis is monetary matters and there it's just to prove it?
So let's see what his answer is, okay, and so let's, you
know, here say the same thing, say if you admit it, it
works. So the answer was, אמר
ליה התם לא קחייב לאחריני הכא קחייב לאחריני. amar lei hatam lo
kachaiv l'achrinei hacha kachaiv l'achrinei. No, there's a difference. When I admit
that I owe Michael a hundred dollars, I'm only hurting myself with
that admission. Okay, when the husband and wife admit that they are
married, they're hurting another person. Who are they hurting? Well, most immediately
they're hurting each other because you don't have them as a unit
admitting something. When I, if I'm the man and I say, yes,
I'm, she's married to me, so what I, if we were to
accept that testimony not just vis-à-vis me, but vis-à-vis her, she would
be restricted to other men, she would be not able to marry
my relatives. When she, when she's saying it, okay, then she is
not only affecting, hurting herself by that admission, but she's hurting me
because I'm now not allowed to marry her relatives. I mean, maybe
if we were a unit we would be believed, but even then,
you know, we're hurting other people because other men now are not
allowed to marry her and it would be considered an act of
adultery with other men to have sex with her. So therefore by
money, my own admission works because I'm the only one that's hurt,
but here personal status issues, right, are not just about restricting yourself.
They affect society is a way of saying it, right? They have
a real, bigger societal implication and we cannot go by just your
own say-so. We need something objective. Now, but wait a minute, all
that says is that we can't accept your own admission. It does
not prove that you need witnesses to make it happen. You understand?
It could still be that they're still married, we just don't accept
that as a standard of proof, right? And let's say there was
a video, right, maybe we'd accept something else as a standard of
proof. So there still is a jump to saying, it's one thing
to say we don't accept your own admission, we need something objective.
It's another thing to say that it's not only proving it, but
it's actually making it happen. And this, this is a big thing
that bothers the אחרונים, acharonim, which is the גמרא gemara never really
closed that gap. We start from money where it's just to prove
that it happened and then we wind up saying, oh, but by
קידושין kiddushin and גיטין gittin without witnesses—I mean, by money it's just
to prove it and then we say by גיטין gittin and קידושין
kiddushin without witnesses, it didn't even happen. So again, it's one thing
to say you might need a certain higher objective standard of proof
because it affects society, but that doesn't mean that it didn't happen
without the witnesses. And I should, by the way, say and that
there's a debate in the אחרונים acharonim how you even conceptualize what
the meaning of the sort of, why you need witnesses to make
it happen by קידושין kiddushin and גיטין. gittin. So some say that
it's still fundamentally is doing the same thing as proving as עדי
בירור, edei beirur, as proving it in court. But the point is
like this. Because this affects other... people in society and the broader
society, if it can't be proved then as a society we cannot
acknowledge that it happened. But fundamentally the witnesses are there to establish
that it actually happened. But without that proof, it didn't happen. Okay,
another approach says no, no, no, I mean, there's other way, I'll
give you one version of the other approach. It's not about proving
it or
it's not only about proving it. It's about because this is such
a weighty act, right, if we're here about to marry each other
off, right, you know, all of a sudden just, you know, the
two of us, it's like sort of like you need a justice
of the peace, right, to get married. You can't just agree. So
people say, oh, you need a מסדר, mesader, but you don't need
a מסדר. mesader. קידושין Kiddushin happens just between two, two individuals without
some rabbi. So what do you need to formalize it? It is
such a weighty act that it cannot be formalized without the presence
of witnesses. And that gives it the weight necessary to make it
happen. So here is a נפקא מינה nafka mina between the two,
and this gets debated in the אחרונים. Achronim. Let's say there were
witnesses, but the witnesses were not known to the bride and the
groom. They were hiding in the bushes. And he said הרי את
מקודשת לי. harei at mekudeshet li. So if all you need to
do is prove that it happened, okay, you can prove that it
happened, you have witnesses. But if it's needed to formalize the act,
then maybe the groom and bride would have to be aware that
they're present and that they have to be, you know, brought into
the act and made part of the act. So I little oversimplified
that נפקא מינה nafka mina because there's ways of sort of of
saying it's not, you know, wouldn't exactly fall out there, but it
gives you a sense of two different ways of thinking about it.
Do they become part of the act and part of formalizing giving
weight to the act? Or is it just we as society can't
acknowledge it because it's so weighty, it's חב לאחריני, chav l'achrini, it
impacts society, that without the ability to prove it, it didn't happen.
Yeah, if you're gonna prove it. Yeah, so that does raise interesting
questions. What could there be something that's an alternative? Sometimes we say
אנן סהדי, anan sahadi, man and women are living together as husband
and wife, we might say, oh well that's like קידושי ביאה kiddushei
biah because אנן סהדי anan sahadi it's clear to everybody what's happening,
right, so maybe that, you know, that raises interesting questions, can something
become now equivalent to עדים edim if it's not about a formal
presence of עדים, edim, if it's more fundamentally that if with you
need to prove it. Okay, what we had before, right? Yes, I
understand. So that is the big debate. In the end of the
day, without the witnesses it didn't happen. But are they doing something
different, giving weight to the act, affecting people's דעת, da'at, seriousness, etc.,
or are we saying it's without the ability to prove it, fundamentally
they're there to prove it, but without the ability to prove it,
it didn't happen. Yes. No, it's really, it's really fascinating, the society's
inserting itself into the otherwise private decision of this couple. Because it's
not a private decision. You know, you want to have sex, that's
a private decision. You want to be recognized as a married couple
in society. Right, I just was, can you reference like where the
major אחרונים Achronim that one would? Yeah, I mean, there's a, there's
the, well, I mean, there's a, there's a large, there's a classic
קצות Ktzot on it, which I would have to, in my head
it says קצ"ח, kuf-tzadi-chet, well, הקצות haKtzot is in חושן משפט, Choshen
Mishpat, I know you'd expect this to be in אבן העזר, Even
HaEzer, but anyway I could send you the sources. The קצות Ktzot
is like one of the primary places where he discusses the different
opinions about this. There's a תשובת הרשב"א, Teshuvat haRashba, there's a מחלוקת
ראשונים machloket Rishonim about the case of עדים edim hiding in the
bushes, and that might be part of the issue. Okay, so maybe
the קצות Ktzot starts from the ממון mamon case. Yeah, I think
he does. Okay, another interesting question though is you would think that
the פשט pshat of the גמרא Gemara sounds to be like it's
flatly not a problem at all מקדש בעד אחד. mekadesh b'ed echad.
The רמ"א Rama in אבן העזר Even HaEzer says a little bit
if it was עד אחד ed echad and שניהם מודים, shneihem modim,
since the גמרא Gemara
didn't a hundred percent reject that position, then we לכתחילה lechatchila are
חושש choshesh for it. If there's any concern of עגונה agunah or
anything like that we're not. But, and this comes up in פוסקים,
poskim, that sometimes they try, you know, to פסל pasul a קידושין,
Kiddushin, right, kids in a high school and he said הרי את
מקודשת לי harei at mekudeshet li and there was one witness and
not two witnesses. Like רב משה'ס תשובות, Rav Moshe's teshuvot, do we
still פסקן pasken at any degree חוששין לקידושין chosheshin l'Kiddushin or not?
Okay, the basic answer is לכתחילה lechatchila we try, we are a
little bit, but if it's a real problem we're not. Okay, but
it's interesting that the גמרא Gemara does not come out to an
absolute conclusion there with עד אחד. ed echad. That's עד אחד ושניהם
מודים. ed echad v'shneihem modim. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says
like this.
Okay, now, now, מר זוטרא ורב אדא סבא בני דרב מרי, Mar
Zutra v'Rav Adda Sava b'nei d'Rav Mari, so these two rabbis who
are the children of רב מרי בר איסור, Rav Mari bar Issur,
פלגי נכסייהו בהדי הדדי. palgi nichsaihu bahadi hadadi.
They divided their property, presumably either they were in partnership and they
divided it, or their father died and they divided it. But there
were no witnesses present. And we're going to see they want to
know if there's an idea of עדי קיום adei kiyum by monetary
matters as well. Okay, so אתו לקמיה דרב אשי. atu l'kamei d'Rav
Ashi. אמרו ליה, amru lei, they came to Rav Ashi, they said
to him, על פי שנים עדים אמר רחמנא, al pi shnei edim
amar Rachmana, it says two witnesses and that's directly by monetary. What
does that mean? Does that mean אי בעי למהדר לא מצי הדר
בהו, iba'ei lemehader lo mati hader bihu, is the purpose of witnesses
just to prevent somebody from lying, from claiming it never happened and
then he can't back out because the witnesses prove that it happened?
ואנן לא הדרן, ve'anan lo hadran, and we're not interested in backing
out. We admit that it happened. Okay, so is the whole purpose
of witness basically to prove it and to stop somebody from, you
know, from lying or backing out? או דילמא לא מקיימא מילתא אלא
בסהדי, o dilma lo mekayma milta ella besahadei, maybe even by monetary
matters, if there are no witnesses, it didn't happen. So do we
have to do it again? Okay, so we did it, but we
did it without witnesses. Was our division of assets binding, right? Let's
say people went ahead and they, you know, they signed a contract
or whatever it was to divide the assets, and they didn't get
it notarized. And they want to know and they didn't get it
witnessed and notarized. So they wanted to know, nobody's interested in backing
out, do we have to do it again and get it witnessed
and notarized? How much is the presence of witnesses עדי קיום edei
kiyum even by monetary matters? Okay, אמר אביי, amar Abaye, אמר להו,
amar lehu, he said to them, לא איברו סהדי אלא לשקרי. lo
ivru sahadei ella leshakrei. Witnesses were only sort of chosen, you know,
chosen only for liars. The purpose of witnesses is to prevent people
from lying. It is not needed for making the thing happen. So
this becomes the phrase of the idea of עדי בירור edei birur
is what make לא איברו סהדי, lo ivru sahadei, this is what
gets quoted all the time in the הלכה halacha literature, you know,
and in the ראשונים ואחרונים, Rishonim veAcharonim, you know, אלא לשקרי. ella
leshakrei. The whole purpose of witnesses is only to prevent liars. That's
all other matters. That's what עדי בירור edei birur is, to prevent
liars, okay? Whereas עדי קיום, edei kiyum, it doesn't matter that it
doesn't matter if everybody's telling the truth, it didn't happen without witnesses.
All right, so that's exactly this little גמרא Gemara we're doing is
exactly conceptually identifying two different roles of witnesses. Is איברו ivru from
like נבראו? nivre'u? No, I understood it to be like chosen to
be
נבחרו? nivcharu? Yeah,
like how does the English translate it? They say here witnesses were
created. Oh, איברו, ivru, from בריאה, beri'ah, oh that's probably correct. Okay,
fine. So but still it's funny, created. Anyway, all right.
Is that also what Steinsaltz—well nobody here has a Steinsaltz. Okay, anyway,
yeah. But anyway this is the idea, this is only for בירור,
birur, I also maybe I think was assuming because of the בירור
birur and איברו ivru I was just assuming that anyway. This is
only to prove that it happened. If everybody's being honest, if we
lived in a world where everybody was honest, you would not need
עדים, edim, okay, as opposed to עדי קיום edei kiyum which actually
makes it happen. Okay, it's an interesting question by the way, you
know, about capital crimes, because by capital crimes also it's not enough
to know it happened, you actually need formal witnesses. So do you
see, right, you know what I mean? You also need התראה hatra'ah
too. So do you want to make a certain type of a
comparison, right, like what's the role of התראה? hatra'ah? Is the role
of התראה—I'm hatra'ah going to this will be way too big of
a digression but I'll just say it in one sentence. Is the
role of התראה hatra'ah just to prove somebody really is, you know,
willful and doing it במזיד, bemezid, right, or is the role of
התראה hatra'ah to mean no, the act only can be deserving, you
know, you're only entitled to give corporal punishment if it's coming with
like this act of rebellion as part of it, like you know,
he's doing it in spite of the warning. And maybe the witnesses
also, how much are they just there to prove it or they're
constitutive of defining the gravity of the act? So it's an interesting
question because by monetary matters it's עדי בירור edei birur and הודאת
בעל דין hoda'at ba'al din works, right? הודאת בעל דין. hoda'at ba'al
din. If everybody admits and everybody's honest, it works. Okay, this is
constitutive, okay, constitutive, is that spelling it right? Anyway, constitutive, whatever, anyway,
and הודאת בעל דין, hoda'at ba'al din, הודאת בעל דין hoda'at ba'al
din does not work, okay? So the question is but by things
like מלקות ומיתה, malkut umitah, right, where you need עדים edim and
התראה, hatra'ah, also הודאת בעל דין hoda'at ba'al din does not work.
So how do you understand that, right? You know, it seems similar
to that. So it's an interesting thing to think about those parallels.
All right, and whether עדים edim are just there to prove it
or they're somehow part of the gravity of the act. All right,
yes. Does discrimination—does self-incrimination come into any of these factors? Does what?
Self-incrimination? Yeah, well, when people say הודאת בעל דין hoda'at ba'al din
doesn't work here, it's because like the רמב״ם Rambam speaks about self-incrimination
and people might, you know, have like trying to get, you know,
have some mental problem and that that's why they're trying to, you
know, they're admitting to something they didn't do and so on. Right,
so there's obviously other reasons why הודאת בעל דין hoda'at ba'al din
might not work here. Okay, let's go on.
אמר אביי, amar Abaye, אמר ליה אחד, amar lei echad, Abaye says
if one witness says to somebody, נטמאו טהרותיך, nitme'u taharotecha,
your, you know, the things that were pure, your grain or whatever,
all of a sudden it became טמא tamei and now you're a
כהן kohen let's say. can't eat it, it's תרומה terumah *trumah* or
something of that sort, or you whatever, it's even if it's חולין
*chullin* you can't eat it when you're trying to stay טהור tahor.
*tahor*. והלה שותק *Vehalach shoteik* and the other person is silent, he
doesn't say you're lying, he doesn't
he doesn't have any response. נאמן *Ne'eman* the עד ed, *eid* is
believed. Now here is a big question of who's believed. Is it
basically the עד אחד ed echad *eid echad* is believed in absence
of a contradiction, which is what the language sounds like? Or is
it that we read his silence as an admission? Okay, so the
question would be, the נפקא מינה nafka mina. *nafka mina* would be
and תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos* directly raises this, let's say he says I
don't know, says really, I didn't know that. Okay, so according to
תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos*, if he says I don't know, then his the
עד ed. *eid* isn't believed. That basically the point of all of
this is silence is admission. So if you say nothing, we think
you're admitting it. But if you say I don't know, then you
say you don't know. So then we don't believe the עד אחד
ed echad *eid echad*. Okay, or another case would be, let's say
the עד אחד ed echad *eid echad* says, you know, your when
you were away yesterday last week in Cincinnati, your טהרות *taharos* became
טמא tamei, *tamei*. So his silence obviously wouldn't be an admission there
because how is he supposed to know that? So תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos*
says this only works in a context where the עד ed *eid*
says, you were there, you knew about it, and the guy's totally
silent. But if the guy says I don't know or we presume
he doesn't know, right, then it's not going to believe. So according
to תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos* this is basically the believe you're believing the
guy's silence, not the עד ed *eid*. The other way of reading
this גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is that you're believing the עד ed *eid*.
Okay, so let's keep on reading.
Oh did I skip a line? I sorry, I skipped the line.
אמר Amar, עד אחד ed echad *Amar eid echad*, I skipped I
skipped the line. I'm sorry, I skipped because we're going to have
the the next case, I went to the next case. I'm sorry,
we're by five lines before it gets white, same point though. אמר
לו עד אחד ed echad *Amar lo eid echad*, so אמר אביי
Abaye *Amar Abaye*, אמר לו עד אחד ed echad אכלת חלב chelev
*Amar lo eid echad achalta cheilev*. One עד ed *eid* says you
ate forbidden fat בשוגג *beshogeg*. Okay, והלה שותק *vehalach shoteik*, what? And
the guy is silent, sorry, והלה שותק נאמן *vehalach shoteik ne'eman*. So
he's believed and you would bring a קרבן korban *korban*. ותנא תונא
*Tana tuna* we taught a similar ברייתא Baraita, *braisa*, אמר לו עד
אחד ed echad אכלת חלב והלה אומר לא אכלתי פטור *Amar lo
eid echad achalta cheilev vehala omer lo achalti patur*. So if you
deny it, you're exempt from a קרבן korban, *korban*. טעמא דאמר לא
*Ta'ama de'amar lo*, the reason is because he said I didn't eat
it. הא אישתיק מהימן meheman, *Ha ishtik meheiman*. The עד *eid* would
be believed and you'd bring a קרבן korban *korban* based on the
testimony of the עד *eid*. So though before we said an עד
*eid* doesn't work by קידושין kiddushin *kiddushin*, here we see that an
עד *eid* does work to make you bring a קרבן korban, *korban*.
Okay ואמר אביי Abaye *ve'amar Abaye*, this is what I jumped to.
אמר לו עד אחד ed echad, נטמאו טהרותיך *Amar lo eid echad
nitmu taharotecha*, an עד *eid* says that your Torah grain became טמא
tamei *tamei*, והלה שותק *vehalach shoteik* and he silent, נאמן *ne'eman*. He's
believed and you would not be able to eat the grain. ותנא
תונא *Tana tuna* we taught similarly, עד אחד ed echad אומר נטמאו
והלה אומר
לא נטמאו *eid echad omer nitmu vehala omer lo nitmu*. One עד
*eid* says they become טמא tamei, *tamei* and another
says they didn't, they contradicted, פטור *patur* or whatever, so they're, you
know, they're
טהור *tahor* is a better גירסא *girsa*. So the grain is considered
טהור *tahor*. טעמא
דאמר לא *Ta'ama de'amar lo*, the reason is because the owner contradicted
the עד *eid*. הא אישתיק מהימן *Ha ishtik meheiman*.
Okay, the עד *eid* would be believed. ואמר
אביי Abaye *Ve'amar Abaye*, so you see an עד אחד ed echad
*eid echad* is believed as long as the owner doesn't contradict. And
doesn't פטור *patur* mean פטור *patur* from a קרבן korban, *korban*? No,
yeah, but the
קרבן korban *korban* is not obvious in that case. ואמר אביי Abaye
*Ve'amar Abaye*, אמר לו עד אחד ed echad שורך נרבע *Amar lo
eid echad shorcha nirva*, here one עד *eid* says your ox was
used in an act of bestiality, and there and therefore he cannot
be brought as a קרבן korban *korban*. Without two witnesses you won't
stone the ox, but he can't be brought as a קרבן korban
*korban*. והלה שותק *vehalach shoteik* and the guy is silent, נאמן *ne'eman*,
he's believed. ותנא תונא *Tana tuna* we taught a ברייתא Baraita. *braisa*
like this, ושנרבע בו עבירה *veshenirva bo aveira*, what type of animals
cannot be used as a קרבן korban, *korban*? An animal that was
used in sin, ושהמית *veshehimit* or that killed a person על פי
עד אחד ed echad *al pi eid echad*, based purely on the
testimony of one witness, על פי בעלים *al pi ba'alim* or the
owner's admission. Because if it was the testimony of two witnesses, you
would stone the ox. נאמן *Ne'eman*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* so
so אביי Abaye *Abaye* says נאמן *ne'eman*. So then the owners would
be believed and the ox would be not be able to be
used as a קרבן korban, *korban*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
האי על פי עד אחד ed echad, היכי דמי heichi dami, *hai
al pi eid echad heichi dami*? What's the case that one witness
you know that affects the status of this ox? אי דקא מודי
בעלי *Ei deka modei ba'ali*, if the owner is saying you're right,
they're admitting to what the witness said, היינו על פי בעלים *hainu
al pi ba'alim*, that's the second case, the owner's admitting. אלא לאו
דשתיק *Ela lav deshoteik*, it must be that he's silent. Okay, and
nevertheless that's acceptable. וצריכא *Vutzricha* and we have to tell me all
three cases that we believe the עד אחד ed echad, *eid echad*
in the absence of the contradiction of the owner. דאי אשמעינן הך
קמייתא *De'i ashmi'inan hachamayita*, if it had just said the first case
of of bringing a קרבן korban, *korban*, we would say
אי לאו דקים ליה בנפשיה *ei lav dekimlei benafshei* the
owner. interpreting the silence as an admission. By the way, the גמרא
Gemara. does the צריכותא. tzrichuta. So the silence by the קרבן case
is obviously an admission because we would say the
following: דאי
לא דקים ליה בנפשיה דעבד de-i la dekim lei benafshei de-avad or
דאכל, de-achal, if he did not really know that he had eaten,
he would not be silent because the consequence of his silence is
going to be he's going to have to bring a קרבן, and
nobody's going to bring a קרבן that might not be a legitimate
קרבן, that would be חולין בעזרה. chullin ba-azarah. חולין בעזרה לא הוי
מייתי. Chullin ba-azarah la havi meiti. So clearly his silence is an
admission because he understands that the consequence of his silence is that
he's going to have to bring a קרבן, and he would never
bring a קרבן if he wasn't wasn't sure he was obligated because
that would be חולין בעזרה. chullin ba-azarah. So there we'll read his
silence as an admission. אבל נטמאו טהרותיך, Aval nitme'u taharotecha, and a
guy says your stuff became טמא, tamei, so maybe his silence is
an admission. מימר אמינא האי דשתיק, Meimar amina hai deshatek, you know
why he's silent? דסבר חזי ליה בימי טומאתו. desavar chazi lei bimei
tumato. All right, big deal. I don't know if they became טמא
or not, or it doesn't sound a big deal, no skin off
my nose, I'll just eat it when I'm טמא, it's no big
loss. So even though he's silent, it's not necessarily because he's admitting,
it's because like it doesn't bother him so much. Okay, ואישמעינן הא,
ve-ashmi-inan ha, if you told me that case, משום דקא מפסיד ליה
בימי טהרתו. mishum deka mafsid lei bimei taharato.
That's cause, okay, his silence is an admission because it does, he
does lose something out. He can't eat it when he's טהור. And
therefore if he's being silent must be because he is admitting. Otherwise
he wouldn't accept that consequence. אבל שורך נרבע, Aval shorecha nirva, but
your ox was used in bestiality, so מימר אמר כל השוורים לאו
לגבי מזבח קיימי. meimar amar kol hasvarm lav legabei mizbe'ach kaimei. He
says, what the heck do I care? I wasn't going to bring
him as a קרבן anyway. Maybe he had a מום, mum, you
know who knows what? So maybe since it's no loss to him,
so he's just silent because he doesn't care. Maybe it's not an
admission. צריכא, Tzricha, you have to tell me all three cases. So
again, because of this צריכותא, tzrichuta, תוספות Tosafot says that the case
is is that we're not really that we're believing the עד, it's
really we're interpreting his silence as an admission. And there's a big
נפקא מינה. nafka mina The נפקא מינה nafka mina is is that
if he says I don't know, according to this, you would not
have these consequences, right? Because it's only because he's silent that we
sort of see it's like he's saying you're right. But if he
said I don't know, fundamentally we do not believe the עד. And
again, the other נפקא מינה is that the עד says it happened
but you weren't around to see it. There also we would not
interpret silence as admission. So the other important question though is is
that why do you need his silence? Whatever happened to עד אחד
נאמן באיסורין, ed echad ne'eman be-issurin, right? If I normally go and
I tell you, you know, this piece of meat here is טרף,
treif, yours, you believe me. One witness is believed by matters of
status of foods and you know and איסורין. issurin. So even though
the issue of קרבן is different, that's an obligation of a קרבן,
and who knows about this something status for the מזבח, mizbe'ach, but
at least the middle case that the grain is טמא, that should
be עד אחד נאמן באיסורין. ed echad ne'eman be-issurin. Why doesn't that
normally apply? And this is the question תוספות tosafot asks and you
know תוספות Tosafot tries to navigate this but I just want to
point out that there's a big difference about all these cases and
עד אחד נאמן באיסורין ed echad ne'eman be-issurin which תוספות Tosafot, does
not say, which is here there's a monetary consequence that I'm coming
to cause a loss to you. Meaning if I tell you don't
buy that food that's being sold at the butcher, you know, it's
טרף treif or whatever it is, you know, that's one thing, although
I am actually causing a loss of business to the butcher. But
if I go and I say your food is טרף, treif, is
it איסור issur or is it like ממונות? mamonot? You're basically telling
me I have to throw out my food. Do I believe you
that I gotta throw out my food? Right? And how do you
know? How are you in a position? Well, I saw it. Okay,
but it's, you know, but anyway, so that raises an interesting question.
All of these are cases where you're telling somebody something about their
property. So do you look at it as a simple like עד
אחד נאמן באיסורין, ed echad ne'eman be-issurin, you know, and the גמרא
Gemara, says no, there needs to be a silence, there needs to
be a type of an admission and so on. תוספות Tosafot brings
in other factors as well. Was the person in a position to
do something about it? Like if you gave them an animal to
שחט shacht and then they said it's טרף, treif, obviously they might
be more believed because they could have made it שחט shacht it
properly or not properly. So a lot of other potential factors here
in when somebody is believed on these issues. Did you want to
ask, is it true that generally the language is concerned with שתיקה
shtika are about
monetary ממונות mamonot issues? That language שתיקה כהודאה, shtika ke-hoda'ah, no you
have שתיקה כהודאה shtika ke-hoda'ah all over. You know, it's not, yeah.
Second thing is if I'm חייב chayav a קרבן, do I, I
don't have to be מקדיש makdish that animal? You do. So then
so then why would it necessarily be a case of חולין בעזרה?
chullin ba-azarah? Because if you're מקדיש makdish a חטאת chatat and you're
not obligated in a חטאת, chatat, it's not קדוש. kadosh. That's the
חילוק. chilluk. You cannot you cannot have a bring a חטאת chatat
without being obligated. So it would be חולין בעזרה. chullin ba-azarah. It's
a good question. You would still מקדיש makdish it, but it wouldn't
basically work because you're not חייב chayav in a חטאת. chatat. Okay,
yeah. All right.
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this: איבעיא להו. Iba'ya lehu.
They raised the following question. אשתו זינתה בעד אחד ושותק. Ishto zinta
be-ed echad ve-shatek. A man says your wife committed adultery and he
is silent. Okay, what's the story there? Now again, if a man
just says... on his own, my wife committed adultery, right? So remember
this gets back to like the case in the משנה. Mishnah. If
he said, she said, you're impacting other people, you're only believed to
yourself, and you're not believed objectively. So if a guy said my
wife committed adultery, the wife, you know, that doesn't, you know, he's
not believed vis-à-vis the wife. But what we do say is, oh,
but now you're bound by your own statement. So based on your
statement that she committed adultery, you're not allowed to continue living with
her. You have to divorce her. Okay, but because we have no
objective proof, you have to give her her כתובה. kesuvah. Now you
might say, okay, so that hurts the wife, right? So how are
we believing him if the consequence is that it's חב לאחריני chav
leachrini like it hurts the wife? But the answer is, he was
always entitled, right, in this system, he was always entitled to unilaterally
divorce his wife. So if he wanted to divorce his wife, he
could have just gotten up and done it. So this is just
essentially what he's doing by saying my wife committed adultery, he's saying
I'm going to unilaterally divorce my wife. Okay, but it doesn't hurt
her, it doesn't whatever, it's not worse than anything else he could
have done unilaterally because he has to pay the כתובה. kesuvah. So
that would be if he said my wife committed adultery. Now, and
if an עד אחד says it, again, an עד אחד is not
believed in issues of personal status and עריות arayos and anything like
that. If to, in order to actually objectively believe it happened, you
would need two witnesses. So here it's basically the point though vis-à-vis
him, the עד אחד says your wife committed adultery and he's silent.
What do we say? Okay, what's the, do we say that that's
an admission and now he has to divorce his wife with a
כתובה? kesuvah? עד אחד נאמן באיסורין ed echad ne'eman be'isurin does not
apply. Correct. This is a personal status issue. A personal status is
yet something. Correct. Personal status is עד אחד is not believed. Okay,
so okay. So אשתו זינתה בעד אחד ושותק ishto zinsah be'ed echad
veshosek and he's silent. מהו? mahu? אמר אביי נאמן. amar abaye ne'eman.
He's believed, and the guy would have to divorce his wife essentially.
רבא אמר אינו נאמן. rava amar eino ne'eman. He's not believed. הוי
דבר שבערוה ואין דבר שבערוה פחות משניים. havay davar shebe'ervah ve'ein davar
shebe'ervah pachos mishnayim. A matter of ערוה, ervah, which is like sex
but also personal status related issues, like we said before, requires two.
Now here it's not עדי קיום, edei kiyum, it's עדי בירור, edei
birur, right? When we say you need two, right,
דבר שבערוה פחות משניים davar shebe'ervah pachos mishnayim has two very different
meanings. One is in the act of קידושין and גיטין, gittin, it
does not take place without the presence of two witnesses. It's like
it didn't happen. The other is in other issues of proving things,
like this is exactly it. עד אחד נאמן באיסורין ed echad ne'eman
be'isurin to talk about the status of a piece of meat. But
if you have a question about somebody's marital status or somebody committed
adultery or somebody a slave or not a slave or issues like
that, just to prove it, the threshold of proof is two witnesses.
So it's both things. You always need two witnesses whether to make
it happen and as the level of proof. So that's what רבא
Rava says, very reasonable. How is אביי Abaye any different? So תוספות
Tosafot says, אביי Abaye and רבא Rava are exactly arguing about the
point we raised earlier. אביי Abaye thinks silence is admission and therefore
if the guy said my wife committed adultery, he'd be bound by
it and he'd divorce her with a כתובה. kesuvah. רבא Rava says
your silence is not admission. It's only the question about the believability
of the עד אחד in the absence of opposition. So in the
absence of opposition, an עד אחד might be believed about טומאה tumah
and about a קרבן, but he's not believed about a woman's personal
status. Okay, that's דבר שבערוה davar shebe'ervah and therefore you, if you,
if you're dealing with external and objective testimony, you need two witnesses.
All right, so that's a very nice way of explaining the debate.
Everybody agrees personal status issues require two witnesses even to prove them,
but אביי says the silence is an admission and therefore he has
to divorce his wife and pay the כתובה. kesuvah. And רבא Rava
says it's about not the silence, it's about the
witness
and
the testimony of the עד and the testimony of the עד is
worthless in this case. So according to him, he just does not
have to divorce. Correct. Correct. Okay, אמר אביי מנא אמינא לה, amar
abaye mena amina lah,
where do I know this, get this idea from, that an un-,
that a silence with an עד אחד works even for like these
personal status issues? דהוה סמיא, dehava samya, great story here. דהוה מסדר
מתניתא קמיה דמר שמואל. dehava mesader masneisa kamei demar shmuel. There was
a blind person, man, who was the one who would like
arrange the משנה, mishnah, meaning he would, you know, be like the
person who had memorized all the Tannaic material and he would be
presenting them in the ישיבה, yeshiva, like he would, you know, be
שמואל's Shmuel's assistant and שמואל Shmuel would say, you know, פתח משנה
ג, pesach mishnah gimel, you know, פרק ג משנה ג, perek gimel
mishnah gimel, and he would—not exactly. Not exactly, he was a תנא.
Tanna. Not exactly like that, that's they didn't have it sort of
organized that way, but anyway. Okay, so he was the one who
had it all memorized, okay, and that was his job. Now, יומא
חד נגה ליה ולא הוי קאתי. Yoma chad naga lei v'lo hava
ka ati. One day he was running late and Shmuel wanted to
start the שיעור Shiur and the this guy wasn't there yet, he
needed the guy. So שדר שליחא בתריה, shadar shlicha batrei, so he
sent some messenger to go fetch the guy. אדאזל שליחא בחדא אורחא,
Ad azal shlicha bechada orcha, the שליח shlicha was going to this
guy's house, he was taking one path. אתא איהו בחדא, ata ihu
bechada, the other guy had already been on his way and he
came to the ישיבה, Yeshiva, they didn't bump into each other, he
went on a different path. So the guy came to the ישיבה
Yeshiva and Shmuel gave his שיעור. Shiur. Fine, wonderful. Now כי אתא
שליחא, ki ata shlicha, then the שליח shlicha returned. אמר, he said,
you know what happened? When I was there, איתתא זנייתא, itata zanyata,
I came to the guy's house, he wasn't around and his wife
was sleeping with someone. So אתא לקמיה דמר שמואל, ata lekama deMar
Shmuel, now he came to Shmuel. Now this is a great case
because this clearly the silence isn't like an admission because the guy
wasn't there, right? Clear, you know, clearly it's not an admission. So
he said to Shmuel, do I have to believe him? So clearly
it's just the weight of an עד that's going
unopposed without the silence being an admission. So אמר ליה, amar lei,
so he said to him, אי מהימן לך, im meheman lach, if
you trust this guy, זיל אפקה, zil apkah, then you have to
divorce her. ואי לא לא תפיק, v'i lo lo tipik, if not,
you don't divorce her. So מאי לאו, mai lav, what does it
mean if you trust this guy? Must mean אי מהימן לך דלאו
גזלנא הוא, im meheman lach d'lav gazlana hu,
if you know that he's not a גזלנא, gazlana, meaning you know
that there's nothing that should make you think that he's a liar.
So he has the normal weight of an עד אחד, so an
unopposed עד אחד would be believed. Okay, now this by the way,
this is Abaye saying this is why I know that an unopposed
עד אחד would be believed. By the way, this is even in
a case without the implicit admission of the guy, of the husband,
right? The husband clearly doesn't know, he was away. And nevertheless what
Abaye is saying, different than the way תוספות framed it earlier, that
an unopposed עד אחד would be believed and he'd be forced to
divorce his wife. Well, that's pretty fascinating. It doesn't say if this
one guy was a שומר שבת, Shomer Shabbat, if he was a
שומר מצוה. Shomer Mitzvah. Well everybody, that was the context, everybody was
then. Okay, well
but still, he's not a גזלנא. gazlana. Right. Well, that would be
the standard reason in a, you know, anyway. So רבא, Rava, רבא
Rava said no, no, that's not what Abaye meant in that case.
He meant אי מהימן לך כבי תרי זיל אפקה. im meheman lach
k'bei trei zil apkah. He meant no, no, no, if he's just
some random guy saying it, then you don't have to take it.
But if you basically trust this guy as much as you would
trust two witnesses, like I have an implicit trust in this guy,
everything he says is like ironclad, you know that he would never
tell some lie. If it's a special case, then you should go
ahead and act on it and divorce her. Presumably though he'd still
have to give the כתובה Ketubah because there's no objective testimony. ואי
לא לא תפיק, v'i lo lo tipik, if not, don't divorce her.
Yes, he's trying to steal your wife. That also could be part
of the motivation, that's a good point. Yikes, what might be his
ulterior motives? Okay, anyway, but here you see it was clarified that
according to Abaye it's not because silence is admission. Abaye's willing to
say that an unopposed עד אחד actually would mean that the, you
know, again couldn't prove that the woman did it but would require
the man to divorce his wife. Very sort of surprising, especially with
the idea of דבר שבערוה. davar shebe'ervah. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara says like this, ואמר אביי מנא אמינא לה. v'amar Abaye mana
amina lah. Now Abaye's going to try to have another proof and
now we're going to have a fascinating story. דתניא, Detanya, we had
taught in the ברייתא, braita, and this whole big passage is going
to be a little historical story which actually has a parallel in
Josephus and you'll see it's probably going to be one of the
biggest passages of Hebrew that we're going to read, you know, in
a גמרא. Gemara So let's take a look. It's analyzed by historians.
Let's take a look. דתניא, Detanya, we taught in a ברייתא.
מעשה בינאי המלך, Maaseh b'Yannai HaMelech, story with King Yannai, right, one
of the חשמונאי Chashmonai kings. שהלך לכוחלית, shehalach l'Kochlit, he went to
this region called כוחלית Kochlit שבמדבר shebamidbar in the wilderness וכבש שם
ששים כרכים, v'chavash sham shishim krachim,
he conquered sixty cities, obviously that's an exaggeration. Okay, anyway, ובחזרתו, uvachazarato,
anyway he had a lot of military success and when he returned
היה שמח שמחה גדולה, haya sameach simcha gdola, he was very joyous.
וקרא לכל חכמי ישראל v'kara l'chol chachmei Yisrael and he called all
the sages. אמר להם, Amar lahem, אבותינו היו אוכלים מלוחים בזמן שהיו
עסוקים בבנין בית המקדש. avoteinu hayu ochlim meluchim bizman shehayu asukim b'vinyan
Beit HaMikdash. You know, when they built the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash
they were very poor and they had to eat like salty fish,
you know, that was like a food of poor people. Herring. אף
אנו נאכל מלוחים זכר לאבותינו. af anu nochal meluchim zecher l'avoteinu. Let
us, bizarre like, you know, let us remember that. So רש"י Rashi
sort of says it's sort of like, you know, משעבוד לגאולה. mishibud
l'geulah. Let's remember how bad off we were and now look at
how successful we are. You know, we've conquered all this land, right,
because that was in the time of the חשמונאים, Chashmonaim, you know,
they had really had self-dominion and they had a lot of military
success. So they went ahead and they had this special feast to
celebrate with the whatever in this context. והעלו מלוחים על שולחנות של
זהב. v'he'elu meluchim al shulchanot shel zahav. It was an interesting contrast,
right? They had these golden tables and they had like herring and
pumpernickel. Okay, so אכלו achlu and they ate. והיה שם איש אחד
לצ לב רע ובליעל. ve-haya sham ish echad, latz, leiv ra, u-v'liya'al.
You see it's very interesting, clearly it's like a literary, you know,
language that you normally don't get in a ברייתא, right? לצ, latz,
excuse me. There was one person who was like a mocker, you
know, he was, you know, you know,
evil, rebellious, you know, schemer. ואלעזר בן פועירה שמו. ve-Elazar ben Po'ira
shemo. And his name was Elazar ben Po'ira. ויאמר אלעזר בן פועירה
לינאי המלך. vayo'mer Elazar ben Po'ira le-Yannai ha-melech.
It's almost written like scripture, right? ויאמר vayo'mer etc. He said to
Yannai, ינאי המלך, Yannai ha-melech, King Yannai, ליבם של פרושים עליך. libam
shel Perushim alecha.
The Pharisees, you know, they're against you. They don't support you. Okay,
that was the חכמים, chachamim, the Pharisees. So he says, ומה אעשה?
u-mah e'eseh? So the king said, what can I do to see
if that's true or not? So he said to him, הקם להם
בציץ שבין עיניך. hakem lahem ba-tzitz she-bein einecha. Make them stand,
הקם להם hakem lahem is a funny phrase, but רש"י Rashi says
it means, make them stand up, wear a ציץ, tzitz, the you
know, the ציץ tzitz of the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, and make
them stand up in your presence, cause the חשמונאים Chashmonaim were also,
you know, כהנים. kohanim. Okay, there's a whole interesting debate of רש"י
Rashi and תוספות, is the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol allowed to wear
the ציץ tzitz outside of the בית המקדש. Beit Ha-Mikdash.
רש"י Rashi says, you know, if you might remember the earlier גמרא,
Gemara that you can wear בגדי כהונה bigdei kehuna out of the
בית המקדש Beit Ha-Mikdash because לא ניתנו תורה למלאכי השרת. lo nitnu
Torah le-malachei ha-shareit.
You can't demand that they strip immediately. So תוספות says fine, but
that doesn't mean like you give them a little bit of time
after they finish their עבודה. avodah. It doesn't mean like סתם stam
out of the בית המקדש Beit Ha-Mikdash you can wear your בגדי
כהונה. bigdei kehuna. So תוספות says well maybe the ציץ tzitz is
different because by the ציץ tzitz it says והיה על מצחו תמיד.
ve-haya al mitcho tamid. It will always be on his forehead. So
maybe there's like a special allowance to always wear the ציץ tzitz
outside of the בית המקדש. Beit Ha-Mikdash. Okay, not like anybody was
asking the הלכה halacha question here. Anyway, so this guy said Yannai,
wear a ציץ, tzitz, okay, and let's see what happens.
It also sort of like reminds you about like that whole story
by the destruction of the בית המקדש, Beit Ha-Mikdash, right? Where this
guy is scheming and he tells the Roman government, send them this
and let's see what they do. Okay, so anyway, wear this ציץ.
tzitz.
רש"י Rashi says the מלוחים meluchim was, you know, kimchi, it was
like ירקות. yerakot. Oh, okay, not fish? Okay, fine. Alright, anyway, where
were we? הקם להם בציץ שבין עיניך. hakem lahem ba-tzitz she-bein einecha.
So he put on the ציץ. tzitz. היה שם זקן אחד. haya
sham zakein echad. Now there was one elder there. ויהודה בן גדידיה
שמו. vi-Yehuda ben Gedidya shemo. His name, and his name was Yehuda
ben Gedidya. ויאמר יהודה בן גדידיה לינאי המלך. vayo'mer Yehuda ben Gedidya
le-Yannai ha-melech.
He said to the king, ינאי המלך, Yannai ha-melech, King Yannai, רב
לך כתר מלכות. rav lecha keter malchut.
You know what, the crown of kingship is sufficient for you. הנח
כתר כהונה לזרעו של אהרן. hanach keter kehuna le-zar'o shel Aharon. Leave
the crown of כהונה kehuna for the descendants of אהרן. Aharon. Not
very politically astute, this guy. Okay, now why did he say that?
The חשמונאים Chashmonaim were כהנים. kohanim. And here's why he said it,
שהיו אומרים, she-hayu omrim, because people, there was a rumor, שאימו נשבית
במודיעים, she-imo nishbeit be-Modi'im, that his mother had been taken captive in
Modi'im. And that would have meant that his mother would have been
פסולה psula for her husband the כהן, kohen, and the child would
have been, meaning Yannai would have been a חלל. chalal. Okay, so
there was that rumor. So that's why he was saying you're not
entitled. But the thing is, ויבוקש הדבר ולא נמצא, va-yivukash ha-davar ve-lo
nimtza, the matter had been investigated and it had not been proven.
So he should have shut up. Okay, but nevertheless, he was sort
of being influenced by the rumors and being very stupid. ויבדלו חכמי
ישראל בזעם. va-yibadlu chachmei Yisrael be-za'am.
And the sages of Israel sort of separated. Now רש"י Rashi says
separated from whom, from him or whatever. רש"י Rashi says it means
basically they were like driven out of that feast, you know, under
the king's displeasure and anger. Maybe because they were silent and they
did not come to defend Yannai. Okay, and this guy was one
of the sages and everybody else was complicit or at least was
not willing to do anything to stand up to him.
ויאמר אלעזר בן פועירה לינאי המלך. vayo'mer Elazar ben Po'ira le-Yannai ha-melech.
So this Elazar said to Yannai, ינאי המלך, Yannai ha-melech, הדיוט שבישראל
כך הוא דינו. hedyot she-be-Yisrael kach hu dino. If he was a
layman, that would be appropriate, like if he had just maybe insulted
a layman, this would be sufficient. ואתה מלך וכהן גדול, ve-atah melech
ve-kohen gadol, you are a king and the high priest, כך הוא
דינך? kach hu dinecha? Is this the law that should apply to
you that this guy gets off with nothing? Now what's exactly happening
here? Cause then it doesn't continue to discuss the punishment of the
guy. So what's exactly happening? So in the parallel story in Josephus,
this by the way, although all these English translations are wonderful, well
whatever, I have my whole critique of Artscroll, but anyway,
people should never forget the value of Pfancino because maybe I'm wrong,
I don't know, I didn't check whether Steinsaltz has it, but Pfancino
is very good in passages like this about bringing in the scholarly
background about it. Anyway, so he points out that in Josephus, the
parallel story is, is that they get, actually the sages did do
something to this guy. They said he was מוציא שם רע motzi
shem ra and they gave him lashes. But this Elazar said to
Yannai, that's all they did, they gave him lashes? I mean, he
offended a king. So the fact that they didn't do something more
severe shows that they're really complicit and they really don't object to
what he said. Okay, so that's sort of the missing piece of
this puzzle. Anyway, ומה אעשה? u-mah e'eseh? So then Yannai said to
this guy, what should I do? So he said אם אתה שומע
לעצתי, im atta shome'a le'atzati, so this אלעזר Eleazar said, if you
listen to my advice, רמסם, romsem, trample them, destroy them, wipe out
the sages. So then ינאי Yannai said, ותורה מה תהא, ve-Torah mah
t'hei, but what will be with the Torah? So he said back,
הרי כרוכה ומונחת בקרן זוית, harei keruchah u-munachat be-keren zavit, what do
you mean? It's right there, it's wrapped up, it's in its scroll.
כל הרוצה ללמוד יבא וילמד, kol ha-rotzeh lilmod yavo ve-yilmad, any—it's—the Torah's
still there, right? You still have the Torah scroll, so you just
kill off the sages, big deal, we still have Torah. So the
גמרא Gemara says, אמר רב
נחמן בר יצחק, amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, so מיד נזרקה בו
אפיקורסות. mi-yad nizreka bo apikorsus. So an אפיקורסות apikorsus was sort of
infected ינאי. Yannai. What was the אפיקורסות? apikorsus? דהוה ליה למימר de-hava
leh le-meimar because he was silent and he should have responded, he
should have said, תינח תורה שבכתב, tinach Torah she-bikhtav, okay, the written
Torah we still have, תורה שבעל פה מאי, Torah she-be-al peh mai,
but who's going to give us the oral traditions? That's clearly—I mean,
the written Torah is not enough. And when he was silent, he
accepted that, oh, well we still have the written Torah. By the
way, a parenthetical note about the word אפיקורסות, apikorsus, right, normally we
say it means heresy, which of course it here, like it's as
if denying the תורה שבעל פה, Torah she-be-al peh, but אפיקורסות apikorsus
in the גמרא Gemara in סנהדרין Sanhedrin where it says an אפיקורוס
apikores has no חלק לעולם הבא, chelek le-olam ha-ba, says what's an
אפיקורוס? apikores? And it basically says, somebody who's מבזה תלמידי חכמים. mevazeh
talmidei chachamim. So אפיקורסות apikorsus has also a specific meaning of not
sort of, you know, revering or appreciating the weight of the sages
and their authority and their tradition and so on. So, you know,
that's the point here is like he was so dismissive of anything
that the sages had to—had to contribute, he—as if it's all just—as
if it's all just a written law. That's interesting, doesn't mean therefore
what you think it means. Right, I mean, right, I mean, in
the רמב''ם Rambam it becomes a much broader term for heresy, but
in the גמרא Gemara not real—not necessarily. Okay, so anyway the גמרא
Gemara says, מיד, mi-yad, so okay, מיד mi-yad so ינאי Yannai listened
to this guy, ותצץ הרעה על ידי אלעזר בן פועירה, ve-tatzatz ha-ra'ah
al yedei Eleazar ben Po'irah, obviously there's some, you know, again some
whole literary thing going on here like a little rhyming. Anyway, so
the evil sprouted forth through this guy, ויהרגו כל חכמי ישראל ve-yahargu
kol chachmei Yisrael and all the sages were—were murdered, were—and והיה העולם
משתומם ve-haya ha-olam mishtomem and the world was desolate without Torah until
שמעון בן שטח—עד שבא שמעון בן שטח Shimon ben Shatach came, he
was hidden because, I think, he was the brother of ינאי's Yannai
wife, she hid him away, והחזיר את התורה ליושנה ve-hechzir et ha-Torah
le-yoshnah and he returned the Torah to its former glory. By the
way, what does it mean? It could just mean he was a
great sage, but some also connect him to the story of the
guy who—there's a question about who, I think, of—he was one of
the people that's attributed to reestablish primary education, to like, you know,
like the primary—like the schools, like basically ensuring that all—all kids of
a young age would be educated and so on. So, you know,
that's interesting and it gets to this whole question about, you know,
who owns the Torah. Is it all in the written? Is it
all in the sages? Do you try to educate the masses? So
it's like would be interesting to hold up that story, which is
not for us now, about the—the establishment of primary education, you know,
together with this issue about destroy—you know, what's happened when the Torah's
wiped out, you know, when the sages are wiped out. Anyway, the
גמרא Gemara says, okay, that was a great story, what does it
have to do with us? So the גמרא Gemara. says, היכי דמי,
what was the evidence that his wife—his mother had been taken captive?
אילימא דבי תרי אמרי
אשתבאי, i-lema de-bei trei amri ishtaba'i, two witnesses said—and what was the
way in which that was, you know, disproven? Because it says it
was investigated and there wasn't anything to the rumor. So what was
that story? If initially two witnesses had said she was taken captive,
ובי תרי אמרי לא אשתבאי u-bei trei amri lo ishtaba'i and then
two said no, so מאי חזית דסמכת אהני סמך אהני, mai chazit
di-samkhat a-hanei samakh a-hanei, so then they should basically neutralize one another.
And the way רש''י Rashi says it is—and it's not so clear
from the גמרא—but רש''י Rashi says that actually we would be left
with a question about ינאי's Yannai status. Why? Why wouldn't the two
just neutralize one another? Because then it becomes this very interesting question
about the—you know, normally we would say you give everybody their חזקה.
chazakah. So רש''י Rashi says here's what we would say. Two say
she was taken captive, two say she wasn't. The mother, in terms
of her personal status, she had a חזקת כשרות chezkat kashrut so
she would be assumed to be okay. But the child, who never
had a חזקת כשרות—now chezkat kashrut maybe it's a case that started
with the mother, we'd say the child was okay, but the mother
wasn't here. It wasn't a case about the mother. It was a
case about the child and therefore the child—right, you got it? Because,
you know, it's a child—we're trying to figure out the status of
the mother, but the case we're dealing with is the case of
the child and then the—so it's בספק, be-safek, two say this, two
say that, the child's halakhic status is בספק. be-safek. That's the way
רש''י Rashi says it. It's a big, big question because obviously our
intuition would be two against two it neutralizes, you have nothing. Okay,
but anyway let's just keep on reading. The גמרא says, if it's
two against two, he would not have been—it would not have been
dismissed, אלא באחד, ela be-echad,
it must be it was one and it was like one against
one and therefore the case was dismissed. וטעמא דקא מחשי לה בי
תרי ve-ta'ama de-ka machishe leh bei trei or maybe two were against
the one witness, okay, and that's why it was dismissed, this rumor
about ינאי. Yannai. הא לאו הכי ha lav hakhi but if not
for that... not been counter-evidence,
מהימן, the one witness would have been believed. So all of this
is to prove that one witness is believed in דבר שבערוה. davar
shebe'ervah. Now notice, it's a big difference. It's not telling a guy
your wife committed adultery where he now has to divorce his wife
and all these other types of things. It's about personal status, but
maybe it is. This woman is a שבויה, shevuyah, now the כהן
kohen her husband would have to divorce her. Okay? So it's an
עד אחד, not not
who's not contradicted, there's no admission of the husband, but just a
non-contradicted עד אחד, and אביי is saying it seems like he would
be believed. So let's see what רבא Rava says back, and we'll
end with that. The גמרא says like this: ורבא VeRava would say
no. לעולם תרי ותרי, Le'olam trei vetrei, it was two against two.
So why was it completely dismissed, at least there should be a
ספק? safek? וכדאמר רב אחא בר מניומי בעדי הזמה, Uchedamar Rav Acha
bar Minyumi be'edei hazamah, like רב אחא בר מניומי Rav Acha bar
Minyumi says in another case, the second two just didn't testify to
a different story. They said to the first two, you couldn't have
seen it, you were with us that day in a different place.
So when the second two say to the first two you couldn't
have seen it, we completely throw out the first two. הכא נמי
בעדי הזמה, Hacha nami be'edei hazamah, that's why. But if you didn't
start with two, it wouldn't have gotten off the ground. You started
with two, it got off the ground, and then it was dismissed.
ואיבעית אימא, Ve'iba'it eima, if you want, you could say כדרבי יצחק,
ked'Rabbi Yitzchak, like רבי יצחק Rabbi Yitzchak explains that case. דאמר רבי
יצחק שפחה הכניסו תחתיה. Damar Rabbi Yitzchak shifcha hachnisu tachteha.
No, here's what happened. First two said, we saw ינאי Yannai's mother
taken captive. And the other two said, yeah, she was taken captive,
but you weren't there for the end of the story. You know
what then happened? People sneaked... so like sneaked in and swapped her
for a maidservant. So the captives thought they had ינאי Yannai's mother,
but we then saved ינאי Yannai's mother. So they're not contradicting, they're
just telling part two of the story, and now we know that
it wasn't a problem. But you're left with this debate of אביי
and רבא Rava where אביי says a pretty crazy thing. I mean,
we said that you need two witnesses to make it happen. What
we are debating now is when we're just trying to prove if
something happened, but it's an issue of personal status, right? Do you
need two witnesses, or does one unopposed witness enough? And אביי is
saying one unopposed witness is enough, which would be disastrous if you
think about the consequences. And in the end, of course, we're going
to go like רבא Rava that in דבר שבערוה, davar shebe'ervah, whether
to make it happen or whether to prove that it happened, you
need two witnesses. One, even an unopposed one, would not suffice. But
we'll continue with this tomorrow. And we remain behind half an עמוד.
amud. Just after all these cases, yeah, the חלב and the תרומה
and the animal and all that? Yep. So where's the luggage? Exactly.
The luggage got lost. All
right. Yes, the next עמוד amud should go very fast. Hopefully, we'll
catch up tomorrow. I don't know. Got
to start on time. Just everything you said here about the validity
of the... what happened with the husband, ינאי, Yannai, being king and...
Yeah.
Is there anything under... you know, in between the lines here about
that...
Oh, in general about combining the two? Yeah. Well, that's what the
רמב"ן Ramban thinks. The רמב"ן Ramban says that's a big... the reason
the rabbis didn't really acknowledge חנוכה Chanukah in the משנה Mishnah were
because they were very critical of the combination of the כהונה kehunah
and the... and the kingship.
Who didn't acknowledge? It's not in...
חנוכה Chanukah barely appears in the משנה. Mishnah. It only appears in
the גמרא.
It's these t-shirts. If it's didn't... if it's not on film, it
never happened. Oh, really?
Yeah, this עוז Oz's witnesses were created. It has עסי Esei as
created. Okay.
And what does it say here about the... what do you call
it? About... does he bring in Josephus? Oh.
So this actually happened. I mean, this story's in
Josephus? Yeah. It's unfortunate. I
mean, yeah, like this does not have the story about שמעון בן
שטח Shimon ben Shatach establishing the educational system, which is obviously very
important.
Yeah. And it doesn't have the filling in the blanks from Josephus.
That's a sad thing that, you know, you think that Steinsaltz is
so academic, but it's only in a certain way. Like, it doesn't
really tap into
whole... academic תלמוד Talmud sort of world, which is funny. Yeah. It's
more about the
historical, archaeological. Yeah, right.
Yeah.